在这个讲座中，我们想谈谈我们如何描述事物的位置
In this lecture, we want to talk about how we describe the position of things in the
世界。在机器人技术中，这非常非常重要。
world. In robotics, this is really, really important.
例如，在我们的机器人问题中，我们可能想要描述机器人的位置。
For instance, in our robotics problem, we might want to describe the position of a robot.
我们可能还想描述机器人想要互动的东西的位置
We might also want to describe the position of something that the robot wants to interact
用。例如，它可能想与我的水瓶互动。所以我需要描述一下
with. For instance, it might want to interact with my water bottle. So I need to describe
机器人的位置，水瓶的位置，我也很感兴趣
the position of the robot, the position of the water bottle and I’m also interested
在描述相对位置。
in describing the relative position.
水瓶相对于机器人在哪里？这显然是那样的
Where is the water bottle with respect to the robot? And that's clearly something that
机器人想知道它是否想要拿起水瓶。
the robot would like to know if it wanted to go and pick up the water bottle.
在描述事物的位置时，我们需要某种参考框架。
When it comes to describing the position of things, we need some kind of frame of reference.
这是描述世界事物地位的一个非常重要的方面。这里
This is a pretty important aspect of describing the position of things in the world. Here
是我们世界的图景。当然，我们需要牢记的一件事是
is a picture of our world. And one of the things we need to keep in mind of course is
我们的世界，我们世界的表面正在移动。地球表面上的一个点
that our world, the surface of our world is moving. A point on the surface at the earth
-赤道在太空中每秒移动近500米。地球本身在移动
– the equator is moving nearly 500 meters per second in space. The earth itself is moving
在太阳周围相当高的速度。然后我们的太阳系正在高速运转
at quite a high speed around the sun. And then our solar system is moving at very high
绕着银河系中心的速度。而且银河系本身正在以令人难以置信的方式发展
speed around the centre of the galaxy. And the galaxy itself is moving at incredible
朝着狮子座的速度迈进。所以，一切都在运转。
speed towards the constellation Leo. So, everything is in motion.
如果我们试图描述事物的位置，那么我们考虑这个问题非常重要
If we're trying to describe where things are, it's really important that we consider the
参照系。
frame of reference.
一切都在发展，所以我们只需要有效地放在地上并说，
Everything is moving so we just have to put effectively a stake in the ground and say,
“这是参考点，我们将决定与该参考相关的所有位置
"This is the reference point and we'll decide all positions with respect to that reference
“这正是我们所做的。我们将把利益放在地上。例如，
point". That's exactly what we do. We're going to put a stake in the ground. For instance,
就像这个标志贴在这里并说，“这是原点。这是坐标，零零
like this sign post here and say, "This is the origin. This is the coordinate, zero zero
我们将测量距离的所有距离。
and we're going to measure all distances from that.
我们将创建一个坐标系。有效地是两个正交轴。一个x轴，
And we're going to create a coordinate frame. Effectively two orthogonal axes. An x-axis,
和y轴，你在学校学到的各种东西。我们将使用这两个
and a y-axis, sorts of things that you learn at school. And we're going to use those two
距离，沿x轴的距离，沿y轴的距离，以便描述
distances, the distance along the x-axis, the distance along the y-axis, in order to describe
二维空间中物体的位置。
the position of an object in two-dimensional space.
在这个讲座中，我们将保持简单。我们只会考虑这个位置
In this lecture, we're going to keep things simple. We're only going to consider the position
在两个方面。在下一个讲座中，我会提出一个问题并谈谈立场
in two dimensions. In the next lecture, I will kick it up a notch and talk about position
三维。
in 3 dimensions.
现在，参考点完全是任意的。那么，我们来谈谈这个参考
Now, reference points are entirely arbitrary. So, let's talk for a moment about the reference
我们在自己的星球上使用的系统。所以，在这里我们描绘了行星地球。
system that we use on our own planet. So, here we have a depiction of planet earth.
这是一个投射，地球当然是一个球体。并制作一张矩形地图
And this is a projection, the earth of course is a sphere. And to make a rectangular map
像这样我们要做的就是切割球体，展开它，伸展它以使它看起来
like this what we have to do is cut the sphere, unroll it, stretch it out so that it looks
像一个矩形。我们在地球上添加了几条参考线。最重要的一个，
like a rectangle. And we put a couple of reference lines on our globe. The most important one,
也许最明显的一个是赤道。
perhaps the most obvious one, is the equator.
因为地球是一个球体，我们有一个明显的轴，就是行星的轴
Because the earth is a sphere, we have an obvious axis which is that which the planet
转过来。并且您可以创建与该旋转轴正交的平面
rotates around. And you may create a plane orthogonal to this rotational axis that cuts
将球体分成两个相等的半球，我们称这条线为赤道并显示出来
the sphere into two equal hemispheres, and we call that line the equator and it shown
这里是黑色的。当你可以站在你的腿上时，你可以去参观赤道
here in black. And you can go and visit the equator when you can stand with your leg one
在北半球和南半球。
in the Northern Hemisphere and one in the Southern Hemisphere.
现在有另一条线，我们称之为Prime子午线并且它正交于
Now there's another line, which we call the Prime meridian and it passes orthogonal to
赤道，它穿过伦敦的格林威治天文台。
the equator, and it passes through the Greenwich observatory in London.
这条线是完全随意的。它不一定要通过格林威治天文台
This line is completely arbitrary. It doesn't have to be through the Greenwich observatory
但我们星球上的惯例是我们使用格林威治天文台线
but the convention on our planet is that we used the Greenwich observatory line as
Prime经络，你可以去格林威治，你可以把双脚放在两边
the Prime meridian, and you can go visit Greenwich you can put your feet on either side
西方的本初子午线和地球的东半球。
of the Prime meridian in the West and the Eastern Hemispheres of the planet.
水平方向上的距离，我们称为经度。和方向，
The distance in the horizontal direction, we refer to as longitude. And the direction,
在另一个方向上的距离，我们称为纬度。所以我们有经度线
the distance in the other direction, we refer to as latitude. So we have lines of longitude
和我们在球体上刻上的纬度线。那两个数字，经度
and lines of latitude that we inscribe onto the sphere. And those two numbers, longitude
和纬度，足以描述任何点，表面上任何地方的位置
and latitude, are sufficient to describe the position of any point, any place on the surface
我们的星球。
of our planet.
现在，正如我之前提到的那样，我们称之为Prime子午线
Now, we have this arbitrary line as I've mentioned before which we called the Prime meridian
穿过格林威治天文台。如果历史不同，我们就会有
which goes through the Greenwich observatory. If history had been different, we would have
有一个不同的Prime子午线。有一个关于Prime经络的建议要通过
had a different Prime meridian. There was a proposal for the Prime meridian to go through
巴黎天文台。如果你今天访问巴黎，你可以看到一条被称为
the Paris observatory. And if you visit Paris today, you can see a line referred to as the
Arago线是这个不存在的Prime子午线穿过城市的地方
Arago line which is where this non-existent Prime meridian passes through the city of
巴黎。它以法国天文学家和数学家阿拉戈（Arago）的名字命名
Paris. And it's named after a French astronomer and mathematician, Arago, who proposed that
特别是本初子午线。
particular Prime meridian.
所以，这里的带回家信息是这个Prime子午线完全是任意的。它
So, the take home message here is that this Prime meridian is completely arbitrary. It
是一个我们都同意的公约。有这个约定是有用的
is a convention that we've all agreed upon. It's useful to have this convention and that's
我们如何描述地球上的点。
how we describe points on the planet of the earth.